<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Submission to the will of God in times of affliction asserted, in a sermon from I Sam. 3. 18 / by a Reverend Divine.</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6332A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11940666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11940666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62092)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 516:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Submission to the will of God in times of affliction asserted, in a sermon from I Sam. 3. 18 / by a Reverend Divine.</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Darby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Matthew Sylvester. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Dedicatory epistle signed: M.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, III, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>God --  Love.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51263:1"/>
            <p>SUBMISSION TO THE Will of God IN <hi>Times of Affliction.</hi> Aſſerted, in a SERMON From 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. <hi>By a Reverend Divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Darby.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51263:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51263:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable RACHEL, Lady <hi>Ruſſel.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe affixing ſo honourable a Name to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, may be deemed by ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as a device to allure Cuſtomers, or to raiſe the Reader's expectation of ſome Novelty contained therein. But tho Dedications are often abuſed to ſo baſe, and many times to a more ſordid end, yet they are of ancient uſe, and may be of great profit. And the deſign of this Sermon, being a perſwaſive to an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute reſignation of our ſelves to the Will of God, and a quiet ſubmiſſion to his fatherly Corrections, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging all that he willeth or doth to be juſt and good, how ſharp ſoever they may appear for the preſent; 'twas judged not unſuitable to your Ladyſhips conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being now conflicting under a ſmart Providence.</p>
            <p>In the enſuing Sermon, your Ladyſhip will find, what kind of Reſignation it is that is required, and what an excellent and commendable thing it is, and the great Advantages we have thereby, breeding in us a contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in every Condition, be we High or Low, Rich or Poor, Solitary or full of Company, in the injoyment of near and dear Relations, and our deprivation of them;
<pb facs="tcp:51263:3"/> cauſing us to ſit looſe from the Creature, or any comfort thereof, be it never ſo amiable, pleaſant, or ſuitable to our deſires; Curing our diſtruſtful Fears, and carking Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes; enabling us to go on chearfully in our Duty, with reſpect to this World, and the next; and to perform that Work which God hath given us to do, leaving the ſucceſs to him who hath the ſoveraign diſpoſal of all Perſons and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents. And as repugnancy to the Divine Will, is the ground of all that Impiety, and conſequently of all thoſe Miſchiefs that ſo much moleſt and trouble the World. So compliance with, and ſubmiſſion to it, is the ground of all true Piety and Peace. The great Quarrel kept up between God and Man, being a Conteſt, who ſhall have their Will, whoſe Will ſhall ſtand, whoſe muſt ſtoop; God to Man, or Man to God. Now, where Wills are at variance, he that hath the greateſt intereſt in the thing conteſted about, and that hath the moſt Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs; that can undertake, that if his Will take place, there ſhall be a good iſſue of things; and if the others take place, there ſhall be a bad iſſue: There's all the reaſon in the World that his Will ſhould ſtand, and the others ſubmit: Now it's clearly ſo in this caſe, between God and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; and to help you in this Duty, is the deſign of the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam;</hi> Whatſoever God hath taken from you, he hath left you ſomething better behind, he hath not taken away himſelf and Spirit, an Intereſt in Chriſt, and a Right to Heaven: And when he takes away any worldly Comfort, he will give ſomething better in the room of it to them that truly fear him; and if what he deprives you of in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, he makes up in Spirituals, you will find a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change: which that you may, ſhall be the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours faithful Servant, <hi>M. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51263:3"/>
            <head>OF Submiſſion to the Will of God. IN <hi>Times of Affliction.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 SAM. 3.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he ſaid, It is the Lord: Let him do what ſeemeth him Good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe Words are the Words of <hi>Eli,</hi> a pious Speech of an humble Soul, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging all that God willeth or doth to be Juſt and Good: And willingly therefore ſubmitting himſelf thereunto. A terrible Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage had <hi>Samuel</hi> brought him from God, ſuch as he was unwilling to impart or reveal, had he not been preſſed by <hi>Eli</hi>'s earneſt Adjuration.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51263:4"/> But when it was diſcovered, ſee the Effect; an humble Submiſſion and entire Reſignation of himſelf to the Will of God. <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the Words we have,
<list>
                  <item>I. An acknowledgment of God's Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
                  <item>II. His Submiſſion thereunto.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. An acknowledgment of God's Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>It is the Lord.</hi> Words ſhort in Expreſſion, but copious and plentifull in Senſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An acknowledgment of God in the Threatning, <hi>It is the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 39.9. <hi>I was Dumb, I opened not my Mouth; becauſe thou didſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His acknowledgment of God as the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Governor of all things, and ſo having the Supream Diſpoſal of all the Creatures. Job 9.12. <hi>Behold, he taketh away, who can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him? Who will ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</hi> God that gave us all our Enjoyments, may deprive us of them at his own Pleaſure. As we cannot reſiſt his Almighty Power, ſo we cannot que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion his abſolute Dominion.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51263:4"/>3. He acknowledgeth his Juſtice, in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this heavy Judgment againſt him and his Family for their Sins. Dan. 9.14. <hi>For the Lord our God is Righteous in all that he hath done: For we have not obeyed his Voice.</hi> Conſciouſneſs of Sin ſhould ſuppreſs all murmuring, and diſpoſe us patiently to bear whatever the Lord is pleaſed to inflict.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Here is alſo an acknowledgment of his Wiſdom: He knoweth what is beſt and fitteſt to be done for his own Glory and our Good. Job 34.33. <hi>Should it be according to thy Mind? He will recompenſe it, whether thou refuſe, or whether thou chuſe.</hi> That is, God will do what is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whether we conſent or no, like it, or not: God will not diſpenſe his Providence as the Creature is pleaſed, or ill pleaſed with it, but as it conduceth to his own Glory: For he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth not the World according to our Paſſions and Humors, but according to the Counſel of his own Will.</p>
            <p n="2">II. His voluntary ſubmiſſion upon theſe grounds; <hi>Let him do what ſeemeth him good:</hi> that is, not what I judg beſt, but what he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth for his own Glory. It is the Duty of a Godly Soul, humbly to ſubmit to the good Will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51263:5"/> of God, even in thoſe things which ſeem to make againſt us. In which two things are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Patience under his Puniſhment, as threatned by the Lord: which is no ſmall part of our Duty; Levit. 26.41. <hi>If their uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Hearts be humbled, and they accept of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their Iniquity.</hi> 'Tis a part of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not to refuſe Puniſhment as juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by us. <hi>Eli</hi> doth not expoſtulate, but ſubmit. 'Tis eaſy to agree with Providence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, or bleſſing us; hard, when it cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeth and ſcourgeth us. <hi>Job</hi> could bleſs God for taking as well as giving: But few have that conſtancy of mind; Job 1.21. <hi>And he ſaid, Naked came I out of my Mother's Womb, and naked ſhall I return thither: The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> 'Tis ſaid, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.6. That when God had left <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in the hand of <hi>Shiſhak, That the King and Princes humbled themſelves, and ſaid, The Lord is Righteous.</hi> That is, they did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg God's juſt proceeding with him. If this acknowledgment were extorted from an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, ſuch as <hi>Rehoboam</hi> was, much more may it be expected from the People of God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51263:5"/>2. His Meekneſs under the Reproof of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> whom he had brought up from a Child: <hi>Eli</hi> was a very old Man, <hi>Samuel</hi> but a Youth, in effect; yet when he was the Meſſenger of theſe ſad Tydings to him; he replieth, <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> Few Men love their Reprovers or Meſſengers of Evil Tydings: but ſo did <hi>Eli.</hi> So did <hi>David:</hi> he was not angry with <hi>Nathan,</hi> but relented towards the Lord; 2 Sam. 12.13. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Nathan, <hi>I have ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi> The Wicked, when they are admoniſhed and rebuked for their ſins, they deſpiſe the Threatning, and hate the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover. But ſo do not God's People, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Rebuke with meekneſs, and confeſs their Sins againſt God, and humbly ſubmit to his Chaſtiſements.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That God's People have attained a good degree of Grace, when they can abſolutely reſign themſelves to the Will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me ſhew you,</p>
            <p n="1">I. What is this Reſignation to the Will of God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51263:6"/>II. What an excellent and commendable thing it is.</p>
            <p n="1">I. What is this Reſignation to the Will of God? I Anſwer, The Will of God may be conſidered two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As certain and known to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As not yet known, neither in the Word or Providence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As certainly known to us, either by Threatnings, or Executions of God's Sentence. 1. By Threatnings, and ſpecial Meſſages, as here in the Caſe of <hi>Eli;</hi> He doth not ſlight God's Wrath, but reverenceth his Word. So <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> is an Inſtance alſo; Iſa. 39.8. <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Hezekiah <hi>to</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>Good is the Word of the Lord which thou haſt ſpoken.</hi> It is a terrible and ſad Word, that his Treaſures, and Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſhould be carried to <hi>Babylon.</hi> The only good that was in it, That the Evil ſhould not come in his time. Yet that was not the main Conſideration, for 'tis added, <hi>He ſaid more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, For there ſhall be Peace and Truth in my Days.</hi> No, but he had other Conſiderations, the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Soveraign Will of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Evil is not only threatned, but inflicted, yet then God's People ſhew they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51263:6"/> have abſolutely given up their Wills to God. Inſtances we have of that, in <hi>Job</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken away; Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord. Pſal.</hi> 119.137. <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord, and upright are thy Judgments.</hi> Acts 21.14. <hi>And they ceaſed, ſaying, the Will of the Lord be done.</hi> The ſight of God's Will muſt ſilence all our Diſputes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In things uncertain and unknown to us as yet, we muſt refer it to God's Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs, to determine all Events, as ſhall ſeem good in his Eyes: He is ſo able, that he can accompliſh what we deſire; ſo good, that we have no reaſon to trouble our ſelves about his Will, but ſubmit to it without Heſitancy: So wiſe, that he will chooſe that which is for the beſt. We have an Inſtance in <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.25, 26. <hi>And the King ſaid unto</hi> Zadock, <hi>Carry back the Ark of God into the City: If I ſhall find Favour in the Eyes of the Lord, he will bring me again, and ſhew me both it, and his Habitation. But if he thus ſay, I have no delight in thee: Behold, here am I, let him do to me as ſeemeth Good unto him.</hi> See how ſweetly and meekly he ſubmitteth to God's Pleaſure, wholly denying himſelf and his own Will: And reſigneth up Perſon, Life, Crown, and Eſtate into God's Hands, to be caſt as a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51263:7"/> Dye, high or low, as it ſhould ſeem good to God. So <hi>Eſther</hi> referreth her caſe to God, <hi>If I periſh, I periſh,</hi> Eſther 4.16. I might produce the Example of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, tho the Event was known to him as Mediator, yet when he ſpeaketh as Man, hear his Words, John 12.27, 28. <hi>Now is my Soul troubled; what ſhall I ſay? Father, ſave me from this Hour: but for this cauſe came I unto this hour. Father, glorify thy Name.</hi> We learn of Chriſt when we are in great Perplexity, and know not the Event, That we ſhould abſolutely ſubmit all things to his Will, with reſpect to his Glory. For ſurely God will determine, and caſt Matters ſo, as it may be for his own Honour, and our Good. Chriſt conſulted not with his own Caſe, but the Glory of God; he reſpected not the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Inclination of his humane Nature, but the Glory of his Father: So ſhould we be content that God be glorified, tho with our Loſs, and bitter Coſt. As natural Things will act againſt their particular Inclination, for a general Good; Air will deſcend, and Water aſcend, to avoid a Vacuity, or to preſerve a Continuity in the World. Now of this Reſignation ſhall I ſpeak, for 'tis not fit that Man ſhould have the diſpoſal of himſelf, or his Condition and Affairs; or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51263:7"/> that he ſhould accommodate his Providence to their carnal Intereſt and Will, or elſe he cannot bear it, or think well of it. No, God's Will muſt always precede, and ours follow. Alas! we have a corrupt Will, guided by a dark Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and if the Blind lead the Lame, what can be expected but Diſorder and Ruine? Therefore our Wills muſt not lead and make the firſt choice, but God's: And to bring our Hearts throughly to yield to this, argueth a good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">II. How excellent and commendable this is, will appear, if you conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Grounds, or Objective Reaſons it goeth upon.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſeveral Cauſes of it, or Subjective Graces it floweth from.</item>
                  <item>3. The Fruits and Effects, or what Excellent Advantages we have thereby.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Grounds of this Reſignation are the three grand Attributes of God, his Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is infinitely Wiſe, and knoweth what is beſt for us, therefore his Divine Choices muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51263:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51263:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51263:9"/> be preferred before our fooliſh Fancies. Iſa. 30.18. <hi>The Lord is a God of Judgment; bleſſed are they that wait for him.</hi> All his Dealings with his Children are full of Wiſdom: And therefore it is fit that he ſhould chooſe our Condition, and not we our ſelves. We would chooſe Life, but God chooſes Death, knowing thereby how to bring moſt Honour to himſelf, and eternal Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to our ſelves; as we ſuffer the loſs thereof for being Faithful to his Intereſt in a Wicked World. You would chooſe Riches, when God knows Poverty is beſt for you, to keep you holy and humble: We ſhould ſoon undoe our ſelves if we our ſelves had our own Will. If God did not often deny us what we have a mind to, as a Child would ruine his Health if you gave him all the Fruit his longing Appetite craveth; no, that muſt be left to the Parents Diſcretion; or a Man in a Fever would hazard his Life if you ſhould give him all that he calleth for, that muſt be left to the Phyſicians Skill. But now on the other hand, nothing can be done amiſs by God, for Infinite Wiſdom cannot err; Deut. 32.4. <hi>As for God his work is perfect.</hi> Some things may fall out croſs to our Opinions and Deſires; but our Deſires are not the meaſure of his Diſpenſations, nor will he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51263:9"/> govern the World according to our Opinion. Moſt Men in the World would have nothing but Health and Wealth, and Love and Reſpect from Men, but it is God's Wiſdom, not our partial Conceits, muſt judg what is neceſſary for us: Therefore many things fall out contrary to our Humor and Inclination, but he that ſeeth in ſecret, knoweth what is good, better, or beſt for us, more than we do for our ſelves. 'Tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient he ſhould diſpleaſe us for our Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Things may be unſatisfactory to us, who are poor ſhort-ſighted Creatures, and often di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered with Paſſions, which God ſeeth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to promote our good, or preſerve the Harmony of his Providence. Our Requeſts many times are but ravings. When we peremptorily interpoſe our Will without God, we ask we know not what, and pray our ſelves into a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief and a Snare. Therefore all muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to God's Wiſdom, and we muſt count that good which God doth, whatever the Event be.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Power of God; which noteth two things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) His Sovereign Right to diſpoſe of his own Creatures.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51263:10"/>(2.) His Might or Omnipotency, to do what he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) His Sovereign Right of diſpoſing his own Creatures. It belongeth to God to do with his own what he pleaſeth, and to uſe them at the pleaſure of his own Will. God's Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Dominion over, and Intereſt in his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, may be ſet forth by three things. A right of making or framing any thing he willeth, in any manner as it pleaſeth him. As the Potter hath power over his Clay, to form what Veſſel he pleaſeth, either of Honour or Diſhonour; Jer. 18.6. <hi>As Clay in the hand of the Potter; ſo are ye in my hand, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before it had a being, had a right to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of it ſelf; neither did God make it what it was by neceſſity of Nature, nor by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Counſel, or Will of any Superior; nor the direction of any Coadjutor; neither is there any to whom he ſhould render an account of his Work, but meerly produced all things by the act of his own Will, as an abſolute and ſoveraign Lord of all his Actions; Rev. 4.11. <hi>Thou haſt created all things, and for thy pleaſure they are and were created.</hi> Now this ſhould be thought of by us, becauſe what-ever was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us in Creation, is not a matter of Right,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51263:10"/> but the meer effect of God's Will and good Pleaſure. He might have made us Stocks and Stones, and not living Creatures; or Plants on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endowed with a Life of Vegitation and Growth. Or, as having a ſenſitive Life, either in the loweſt rank of thoſe living Creatures, Toads, or Vipers; or in the higheſt rank, Horſe or Mule, without Underſtanding. Or reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Creatures, as Men, or Angels among Men, all the Bleſſings and Privileges that we were born unto, might have been with-held, without any injuſtice. The various Conſtitutions or Complexions of Men, together with all their Gifts and natural Capacities, are the Fruit of his ſoveraign Will.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) A right of having and poſſeſſing all things ſo framed and made by him. Among Men, whoſoever maketh any thing by his own proper Art and Labour, and that of his own Stuff is counted to have a full right to it, &amp; a full power to diſpoſe of it. Yet no Workman ever made any thing without ſome Matter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſting: But God made all things out of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and therefore ſurely his right is greater. For this reaſon God is called, not only the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> but the <hi>poſſeſſor</hi> of Heaven and Earth; <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.14, 19. God is the great Proprietor,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51263:11"/> and in a ſenſe the only Proprietor, who hath <hi>dominium propriê dictum.</hi> Man hath only the Uſe, and Stewardſhip, and Employment of theſe things which are committed to him, by the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of God's Providence. He hath given <hi>diſpenſationem,</hi> the employment of theſe things, not <hi>dominium,</hi> or the ſoveraign power over them. As to Life, the caſe is clear, Man is not <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Vitae,</hi> but <hi>Cuſtos;</hi> not the Lord of his own Life, to lengthen or ſhorten it at pleaſure, but only a Guardian to keep it for <hi>God.</hi> And this is true, not only of Life, but of Time, Strength, Wealth, Parts, yea of all that we have. All the right we have, is to prevent the incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our fellow Creatures: A right, by way of Charge and Truſt, as a Steward to the things committed to him; as a Workman to his Tools and Inſtruments, to do his Work; or a Factor to the Eſtate wherewith he is intruſted, but not an abſolute, independant, uncontrolable Right. They are not ours, to uſe as we think meet; or ours, to keep as long as we pleaſe: For in giving to us, <hi>God</hi> never diſpoſſeſſed himſelf; therefore he challengeth his Propriety and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; <hi>Gold and Silver are mine,</hi> Haggai 2.8. And again, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.9. <hi>I will take my Corn, and my Oil; I will recover my Flax.</hi> All is <hi>God</hi>'s to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51263:11"/> diſpoſe of; in what-ever hands it is, <hi>God</hi> can take and give at pleaſure. Now this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration doth not only check our Uſurpations, who ſeek to ſave and ſteal as much as we can from <hi>God:</hi> Or quicken our faithfulneſs, that the ſupream Lord may not be deprived of his Right, but alſo much promote our reſignation, in leaving our ſelves, and all that is ours, to his diſpoſal. We do but reſtore him his own, or acquieſce in his Power and Sovereign Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) God hath a right of uſing all things thus in his Poſſeſſion, according to his own Pleaſure. For Reaſon will tell us, that the Uſe, Benefit, and Utility of any thing, belongeth to him whoſe it is. So God is the ſole Diſpoſer of all things; he made them for himſelf, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them Ultimately and Terminatively, for himſelf: Some things immediately, all things ultimately. <hi>Of him, through him, to him are all things,</hi> Rom. 11.36. And, Prov. 16.4. <hi>God hath made all things for himſelf.</hi> All the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, Riches, Poverty, Health, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Eaſe, Pain, Life, Death, and the kinds thereof, are all at God's diſpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8, 9. So that the Sword was but as a Key to open Heaven's Door to <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> to free him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51263:12"/> from a hard task-maſter, that he might go home to his gracious Lord. Now this right of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, is of great practical uſe, to keep us in a due Subjection to God's Laws, and Providence, without murmuring or repining: We cannot ſay to him, <hi>What makeſt thou? or why dost thou this?</hi> Iſa. 45.9. 'Tis enough to us, <hi>God</hi> doth it whoſe Right none can queſtion, or controle his Intentions, or impeach his Liberty, or challenge him becauſe he governeth us in this or that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or in another way than we would have had him to have done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Almighty Power. God is able to do what he pleaſeth, none can ſtay his Hand, or ſtop his Work: So that whether we will or no, all our Affairs are at God's diſpoſal. If he be pleaſed to ſtrip us, and bereave us, either of Life, or the Comforts of Life, Eſtate, or dear Relations, or Liberty of Service: There is no ſtanding out againſt him. Therefore the beſt way is to ſubmit, and refer all to him. Job 9.12. <hi>He taketh away, who can hinder him?</hi> So Job 33.12, 13. <hi>God is greater than man, why doſt thou ſtrive againſt him, for he giveth not account of any of his Matters.</hi> Now this ſhould lay Men low be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and ſilence all their Quarrellings. We all acknowledg that God's Power is Infinite;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51263:12"/> yet what Worm is there that will ſubmit wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to him, do further than themſelves pleaſe? 'Tis evident, do what they can, <hi>God</hi> will be Maſter, and take his own Way. All Events are in his hands. Our ſtrivings may be ſinful, but they cannot be helpful to us. Mat. 6.27. <hi>Which of you by taking Thought, can add one Cubit to his Stature?</hi> We cannot make our ſelves taller or ſhorter; yea, not change the colour of an Hair, to make it white or black. We may buſy our ſelves with anxious thoughts about Events, but what do we get by it? We cannot cure a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe in our Bodies, nor prevent a breach in our Relations: Nor increaſe our Trading, nor draw Buyers to our ſelves. The Hearts of all Men are in <hi>God</hi>'s hands; and when we have done all, we muſt ſtand to <hi>God</hi>'s allowance; therefore 'tis beſt at firſt to refer all Events to him. <hi>God</hi>'s So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty ſheweth, that it is unjuſt if we conſent not to it; but <hi>God</hi>'s Almighty Power, that it is fruitleſs if we do otherwiſe. <hi>God</hi>'s Will doth and muſt govern the Affairs of the World: if he require our conſent and ſubmiſſion; 'tis for our Profit, that we ſhew our Obedience and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51263:13"/>3. The third Ground is, He is incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly good and gracious to his Children, that love him, and fear him, and will convert all that befalleth them to their Everlaſting Good: So that God, as powerful, can do what he pleaſeth; God, as kind, will do what is for the beſt. Rom. 8.28. <hi>All things ſhall work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good to them that love God.</hi> And <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake, O North Winds, and come thou South, blow upon my Garden, that the Spices thereof may flow out.</hi> Out of what Corner ſoever the Wind bloweth, it bloweth good to the Saints. The goodneſs of God is many ways ſeen in the Diſpenſations of his Providence; partly in this, reſigning is not the way to loſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which would moſt pleaſe us, but to keep it ſtill. <hi>Abraham</hi> by offering <hi>Iſaac</hi> to God, had him nevertheleſs; Heb. 11.19. <hi>Accounting that God was able to raiſe him up, even from the dead: from whence alſo he received him in a Figure.</hi> There is a kind of a Reſurrection of our Comforts from the Dead, which maketh them the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to us. We gave them to God, and he giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them back again; partly, becauſe we ſhall have better things of God, for we muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, out of an hope that God will not take the Offer, as the promiſe of an hundred fold
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51263:13"/> in this Life, with Perſecutions to thoſe that have left Houſes, and Lands, and Relations, for Chriſt's ſake and the Goſpel's: Mark 10.30. <hi>But he ſhall receive an hundred fold now in this Time, Houſes, and Brethren, and Siſters, and Mothers, and Children, and Lands, with Perſecutions; and in the World to come Eternal Life:</hi> Meaning thereby Peace of Conſcience. And the leaſt Bleſſing of God with a quiet Conſcience, is more worth than all the Goods in the World: Partly by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, God will not be wholly wanting to his People, nor leave them utterly deſtitute. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>God is Faithful, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above what you are able, but will with the Temptation make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to bear it.</hi> Two things are promiſed here. Firſt, The Gentleneſs and Wiſdom of his Conduct. Secondly, A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Iſſue. For the preſent, when our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is at worſt, if it be not comfortable it will be tolerable: For the future he will give you a way to eſcape. You are not caſt into the deep Ocean, where there are no Banks nor Bottom. As long as a Man can look to the end of an Evil, he is not quite diſcouraged. As a Man in the deep Waters ſtrugling for Life, hath hope as long as he can ſee Shoar. So that Afflictions are qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51263:14"/> both as to the Grievouſneſs and Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, by the Support and the Iſſue we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from God's Goodneſs. Now that this may the more prevail with us, God is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented under the Notion of a Father; he doth not only act as a Lord, out of Sovereignty, or a Judge, according to Juſtice, but as a Father, who loveth his Children, and will not neglect them, or any of their Concernments: Mat. 6.12. <hi>Your Heavenly Father knoweth that you have need of theſe things.</hi> As Children naturally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Food and Rayment from their Parents: So the Children of God may in all Eſtates refer themſelves to his Fatherly Providence. A Mother cannot be ſo tender of a Sucking Child, as God is of his Children: Iſa. 49.15. <hi>Can a Woman forget her Child, her Sucking Child, her only Child, the Fruit of her Womb? they may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,</hi> deface the feelings of Nature, <hi>but I will not forget you, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Fix but this one Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that you have a Father in Heaven, and then why ſhould you diſquiet your Thoughts about future Events? Your Father knoweth how to breed up his own Children, and will or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all things for their Good.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51263:14"/>2. The Cauſes of it, or the Subjective Graces it floweth from.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith, or a ſound belief of God's Being, and Providence, and gracious Promiſes. They know there is a God, and that he hath a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar care of Human Affairs, and hath made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that he will not leave his People to inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Difficulties: Therefore they depend upon him, and refer all Events that concern them, and theirs, to the diſpoſal of his Fatherly Government, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5, 6. They know not how he will caſt the Event, but they wholly leave it to him. Now this Submiſſion is an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial act of Truſt, and the great Truſt required of us as to Temporal Things: For we cannot be confident of Succeſs. We are to go on with our Duty, and refer the Event to God. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion after the Event, is Patience; but before the Event, is Faith: for it argueth high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable thoughts of God, when we can blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, truſt our All in his Hands, and refer all to his Pleaſure, tho we know not what will come of it. Pſal. 37.5. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord, and he ſhall bring it to paſs.</hi> And Pſal. 55.22. <hi>Caſt thy Burden upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſuſtain thee.</hi> And 1 Pet. 5.7. <hi>Caſt all thy care upon the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51263:15"/> Lord, who careth for thee.</hi> All this argueth a ſound belief of God's Being, and Providence; that he will caſt all our Matters ſo, as may be for his <hi>Glory,</hi> and our <hi>Good.</hi> Now on the contrary, carking Care, and anxious thoughts about the Event, ſhew little Faith. Mat. 6.30. <hi>Shall he not much more cloath you, O ye of little Faith?</hi> You have not honourable Thoughts of <hi>God's Wiſdom, Power,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> when you cannot depend upon his Conduct, and Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cometh from Humility: 'Tis a great act of Humility, to be content to be at God's finding, eſpecially in ſuch a proud Creature as Man, who would be as a God to himſelf, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for himſelf, both as to the avoiding Evil, and obtaining Good. Witneſs our firſt Parents, who greedily nibled at that Bait, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Behold, the Man is become as one of us;</hi> a ſmart Irriſion! But the humble Man is content to be dealt withal, as the Lord pleaſeth, and wholly ſubmitteth to his Will, and waiting for the Iſſues of God's Providence, as he is pleaſed to diſpenſe them.</p>
            <p>But more plainly, there are two Properties in Humility: They that are of an humble and lowly Spirit, they think not great things of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51263:15"/> themſelves, nor ſeek great things for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They have not high thoughts of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; 'tis Self-conceit that eſtabliſheth Self-will. We think our ſelves wiſer and better than we are; or that we deſerve more, and can do more for our ſelves, otherwiſe we would ſtoop to God, and let him chuſe our Inheritance for us. Preſcribing to God, always argues aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſelves. We take too much upon us, when we wield our own Fortune, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God, or ſubmiſſion to him.</p>
            <p>So again, They that will ſtand to God's Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, do not ſeek great things for themſelves. It may be, God may beſtow great things upon them here in the World, as he did upon <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> but this was not their aim. When God's Will goeth with ours, for Wealth, Riches, and Honour, then we may take it ſweetly out of the hands of his Providence, and uſe it for his Glory: but when we ſeek Meat for our Luſts, and peremptorily fix our carnal Deſires, and would ſet God a Task to comply withal; it is the greateſt pride imaginable, meerly to ſet their Hearts and Wills to be Rich and Great, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. You deſpiſe God if you think to do it without him, and undertake a Task too hard for you; yea, provoke him to diſappoint
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51263:16"/> you. But if you think to do it by God, you would make him to ſerve with your Sins, or to maintain your Luſts; therefore nothing is left, but to be content to be at God's finding, and let his Will interpoſe, before you expreſs any Will of your own.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It cometh from Mortification, and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the World, and weanedneſs from the Comforts of it; or an indifferency of mind to all future worldly Events. For as long as there remaineth in us an over-eager deſire of any good that we want, or of any thing that we would fain have, or be in the World, and the Heart runneth out inordinately and impetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon it, we can never reſign up our ſelves to the Will of God: As <hi>Rachel,</hi> Gen. 30.1. <hi>Give me Children, or elſe I die.</hi> Words of impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiency, and fixedneſs of Will on a particular worldly Comfort.</p>
            <p>The motions of Luſt are rapid and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.2, 3. <hi>Ye luſt, and have not; ye kill, and deſire to have, and cannot obtain; ye fight and war, and have not, becauſe ye ask amiſs, that ye may conſume it upon your luſts.</hi> See how eager Men are, to have what they love, or to purſue after thoſe things which are a ſatisfaction to their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51263:16"/> Luſts. Firſt, There was Coveting, and that bred Envyings and Emulations; and thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations bred Fighting and Warring, which made way for Bloodſhed and Deſtruction; and then they would draw God into the Quarrel, and his Providence muſt laequey on their carnal Humors: but all in vain, and therefore 'tis good not to be too eager to have what we love; for this is the way, to be either denied, or to have it with a Curſe; uſually Men are paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, becauſe they would not have the Fleſh want its Contentment. But the Rule is, <hi>not my Will, but thine be done.</hi> The mortified Heart, what-ever it wanteth or deſireth, it leaveth to God. A Chriſtian ſhould be poſitive in nothing but his Duty.</p>
            <p>There is a fixed Reſolution becometh us if God will deliver: well, but if not, we will pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently bear his pleaſure. When <hi>Jonah</hi>'s Goard is blaſted, nothing will pleaſe him but Death. Deſires pettiſhly ſolicited, and finally croſſed and diſappointed, breed Vexation; and over-valued Comforts, will ſoon breed our Trouble. Jonah 4.8. <hi>Doſt thou well to be angry becauſe of the Gourd? And he ſaid, I do well to be Angry: And he requeſted for himſelf that he might die.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt ſit looſe from the Creature,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51263:17"/> that we may entirely refer all to God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Fruits, or excellent Advantages we have thereby.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It breedeth a Contentation in every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition wherein God hath ſet us: though it be not ſo pleaſing to us, yet it is that which God appoints, be we Rich, or be we Poor, Solitary, or full of Company of Friends and Relations: Phil. 4.12. <hi>I know both how to be abaſed, and how to abound every where, and in all things. I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed both to be full, and to be hungry; both to abound, and ſuffer need.</hi> They never quarrel with God's Government, but take their Lot as they find it. And be their way to Heaven fair or foul, ſmooth or cragged, up-hill or down-hill, yet they go on in their Journey. Surely, 'tis the duty of Chriſtians to be contented with what God will have us to be: Heb. 13.5. <hi>Be content with ſuch things as you have.</hi> We muſt not reſign our ſelves to God in Name and Pretence, but in Deed and Reality; and when our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation is tried, it muſt be verified. Now the Reality is tried, when the Will of God is declared by the Event. Many reſign them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God, with an hope that God will not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51263:17"/> take them at their word, but that is falſhood and hypocriſy; if God taketh any thing from them, they are troubled: but the true Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, breedeth a willingneſs to reſign our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts when God calleth for them, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo dear to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cauſeth us to ſit looſe from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. A being fixed, or cleaving, or holding to any State or Condition in the World, or any Comfort of ours, be it never ſo aimable, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant or ſuitable to our deſires, leaveth no room for Submiſſion or Reſignation to the Will of God. For ſo far as your Souls are bound up with any Creature, ſo far you are in danger of denying, or not conſenting to his Sovereignty and Authority over us. 'Tis a Death to many to think of a Change or Divorce from that State in which they are. But a ſober mortifyed Chriſtian holdeth all his Comforts at God's Will and Pleaſure, and is ready to reſign them when God calleth for them. As <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh of carrying his Life in his Hands: ſo ſhould we all Worldly Things, as ready to give them up if the Will of the Lord be ſo: Otherwiſe we make a Snare for our ſelves, and the over-valued natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Comfort, is a Door open to let in trouble
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51263:18"/> to the Soul: 'Tis our Affection cauſeth our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. The Apoſtle coupleth Temperance and Patience together, 2 Pet. 1.6. <hi>To Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance Patience.</hi> And 1 Cor. 7.30. <hi>And they that weep as tho they wept not, and they that rejoyce as tho they rejoyced not.</hi> If we rejoice as tho we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced not, we ſhall weep as tho we wept not: Otherwiſe to be croſſed in a ſmall matter, breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth great Vexation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It cureth our diſtruſtful Fears, and Cares. Carking Solicitude cometh from want of Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. We would be our own Carvers, and take God's Work out of his Hand, not daring to rely upon his Providence, and Promiſe, nor to ſubmit to the Event as he ſhall diſpoſe it for us. Whereas if you could refer your ſelves to God, and attend upon the Iſſues of his Holy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you would find this carking both needleſs, and fruitleſs. What need we trouble our ſelves about what God will do for us, or needleſsly take a Burden upon our ſelves, of which God is willing to eaſe us? God hath a proſpect of all future Contingencies at once, which we have not: And is faithful to diſpoſe of them for his own Glory, and our Good. Could we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, and depend upon this, it would eaſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51263:18"/> us of many troubleſome Thoughts, Prov. 16.3. <hi>Commit thy Way unto the Lord, and thy Thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</hi> And Pſal. 112.7. <hi>His Heart is fixed, truſting in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It would prevent Repinings and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings at God's Diſpenſations, becauſe it is not according to our Mind. For we are not to ſit Judges of God's Actions, or to like and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Diſpoſals of his Providence at our Will and Pleaſure. The Words for Murmerers and Complainers, <hi>Jude</hi> 16. is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Blamers of their Lot and Portion, becauſe they ſet up another Scheme and Model of Providence in their own Minds, and have not reſigned up themſelves to the Will of God. You ſhould count that Good, which God doth, for his Will is the Supream Rule and Reaſon of all Things.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That we may go on cheerfully in our Duty, whether of our general or our particular Calling, Let us mind the work God hath given us to do, and let God take care of the Succeſs. 1 Chron. 19.13. <hi>Be of good Courage, and let us behave our ſelves valiently, for our People, and for the Cities of our God: And let the Lord do what is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51263:19"/> Good in his Sight.</hi> A Chriſtian ſhould take more care what he ſhould do, than what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him; he can never be comfortable in the work of his Calling, nor have a quiet frame of Spirit, till he can refer all things to God, but will ſtill be diſtracted with anxious and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious Thoughts. Luke 12.29. <hi>Neither be ye of doubtful Mind:</hi> In the Margin, 'Tis <hi>Be not in careful Suſpence.</hi> 'Tis a Bleſſed Frame of Spirit to be eaſed of thoſe tumultuous, and unquiet Thoughts, which will haunt us in our Calling. So for our general Calling: Make ſure of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and refer other things to God, Mat. 6.33. <hi>First ſeek the Kingdom of God, and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and all theſe Things ſhall be added unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. To breed a Godly Reſolution in us in all Sufferings, tho we know not the Event, as the Three Children, Dan. 3.16, 17. <hi>We are not careful to anſwer thee in this matter. Our God is able to deliver us: But if not, be it known unto thee, O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="application">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51263:19"/>
               <head>USE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> is, To perſwade us to this Reſignation of our Wills to the Will of God, and to put our ſelves as a Dye in the Hands of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that the Caſt may fall as God pleaſeth. I know, 'tis difficult to bring our ſelves to ſuch an aequanimity, and we ſhall find diſtruſts when means fail. And 'tis hard to perſwade Men againſt preſent ſenſe, that tis good to be Poor, and Sick, and Impriſoned, and Afflicted, and to be deprived of dear Relations. That Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is good, that we may not be proud; that Diſeaſes are good, that we may learn Patience; Trouble good, that we may have often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to God; Frowns of the World good, that we may have more humble familiarity with God; that Breaches upon near Relations are good, that we might more intirely ſeek our happineſs in God. That if God had not taken away our Comforts, they might have taken us away from him: If we had not met with ſome outward and worldly Loſs, we might have loſt our Souls; that the leſſening of our Eſtate might occaſion the diminiſhing of our Luſts. Surely theſe things ſhould not be ſtrange to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51263:20"/> them, that know what a God they ſerve, and meaſure all things by their chief Good and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Happineſs.</p>
               <p>Let me preſs you to two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Mortification and weanedneſs from the World, is neceſſary. There is no talking of referring all things to God, while worldly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections reign in us: If once your chief care be for Heavenly Things, you will ſoon be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with a moderate ſupply of Earthly Things: Carnal Affections are vehement, and muſt have ſatisfaction. A Man that ſavoureth the things of the Fleſh, will think himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, when his Relations, Pleaſure, Honour, and Plenty, are taken away; but a gracious Heart, that's weaned from the World, ſees e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in God's Favour to make up the loſs of theſe things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Believe the particularity of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which reacheth to all things; eſpecially to thoſe who have a care of his Glory, and ſeek his Kingdom. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> telleth us, <q rend="inline">That it is the Opinion of ſome Philoſophers, That God hath a care of the Univerſe, but not of the Kinds and Species of all things, much leſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51263:20"/> of the Individuals, that is, of Me, or Thee.</q> If this were true, we were left to our own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; this would deſtroy all Prayer and Praiſe, Love and Truſt. No! all things are ſubject to his Providence. He upholdeth all things by the Word of his Power. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. All things are ſubject to his Providence, and ſupported by the ſame Word by which they were created. He holdeth all things in his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty graſp: Job 6.9. <hi>That he would let looſe his Hand, and cut me off;</hi> God could eaſily do it. All Creatures are at his finding; Matth. 10.29. <hi>A Sparrow ſhall not fall to the ground without your Heavenly Father.</hi> The leaſt of the Creatures doth not die caſually; they cannot kill a Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, more than God's Providence ſeeth fit to permit and order. Now we may reaſon as the Apoſtle; Doth God take care of Sparrows, and Oxen? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. ye are of more value than many Sparrows: much more Believers in Chriſt. <hi>The Hairs of your Head are numbred,</hi> Matth. 10.30, 31. God hath the knowledg, and care, and over-ruling of the leaſt things that belong to you, or ſhall befal you. They are the Kernel of Man-kind, the Firſt-fruits of his Creatures, for whoſe ſake the World is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and without whom it would be brought
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51263:21"/> to an end. In a Family, Children are much more cared for than Dogs and Swine. 1 Tim. 4.10. <hi>God, who is the Saviour of all Men, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of thoſe that believe.</hi> The Lord's Portion is his People, God careth for them in a peculiar manner, heareth their Prayers, how deſpicable ſoever they are in the World, Pſal. 34.6. <hi>This poor Man cryed unto the Lord, and the Lord heard him, and ſaved him out of all his Troubles.</hi> He careth for all things wherein they are concerned, Job. 1.10. <hi>Haſt thou not made an Hedg about him, and about all that he hath, on every ſide?</hi> Providence doth ſo guard them, and every thing that is theirs, that without God's permiſſion, Satan or his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot touch them: He obſerveth their Tears, Fears, Haltings, Wandrings, Pſal. 56.9. <hi>Thou telleſt all my Wandrings, put thou my Tears in thy Bottle, are they not in thy Book?</hi> Now this is a mighty relief to Faith; can we be backward to truſt him, who hath ſuch a particular care over us, our Perſons, Name, Eſtate, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51263:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
